welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
I get a thumbs up if everyone can hear
me clearly cool so I'm just going to
share my screen here
and you guys see this
you
all right so in in an effort to not bury
the lead what I want to talk to you guys
tonight about is the concept of a
digital game something to help people
maintain their sovereignty and respond
appropriately to the meta crisis if
you've been following along with this
discussion if you've been listening to
anything from Jordan Hall or if you've
been attending some of these sessions at
the stoah you may have had this feeling
of okay
great there seems to be a lot that I can
do right now where do I start and if
you're like me then maybe you've been
feeling a little bit overwhelmed maybe
you've had some false starts if I'm
successful with this conversation and
with the group discussion that precedes
after it then maybe by the end of the
hour we will have a better sense of
where to start and and how to do so
successfully so to put it really crudely
I'm going to talk for a little bit
hopefully I can get through it in 15
minutes and then we'll have an open
discussion and at the end there will be
a call to action something that will
actually allow us to to move forward on
some of the themes that are going on
here but before getting to that I just
want to do say a few points about
housekeeping so first if you can please
turn on your video we're not recording
the group discussion section of it so
you can afford a little more
vulnerability you don't have to worry
about you know if your room looks ugly
or something that and it really improves
the collective vibe and makes it feel
more like a digital campfire the second
thing is use the chat feel free to have
a parallel discussion if I say something
that prompts like an interesting idea or
a quote or something you want to share
with everybody else just throw it in the
chat if I ask a question feel free to
respond in the chat and then the final
thing is make friends so even if you
don't get any new ideas tonight but you
have one new relationship that's a huge
success and you might be wondering how
do you do that one technique is if you
hear somebody say something that you
really like just send them a private
message in the chat and say I liked what
you said maybe we can talk about it
further here are my thoughts here's my
Twitter following
something like that and maybe you could
make some friends on the internet okay
without further delay I'm gonna try to
formulate kind of a summary of the
problem that that we're currently faced
with so you can think of this as Copa 19
you can think of this as the meta crisis
I particularly liked one angle that
Jordan Hall had in one of his
situational assessments where he was
talking about how the physical health
crisis that started with Kobe 19 is
quickly turning into a mental health
crisis there's many aspects to this but
this one was very salient to me and I
imagine that's intuitively true for a
lot of you but just to highlight a few
things there's millions of people in
social isolation
there's joblessness loss of income loss
of purpose there's this collective
breakdown in sense-making
with a really aggressive news cycle that
is making us afraid and like we don't
know you know how to tell up from down
or what to believe and I would say
mortality salience has gone up like
crazy you know a lot of people who
aren't used to looking into the void are
now being forced to do so and then we're
surrounded by the most advanced tools of
escapism ever created
so like Netflix processed food delivery
pornography social media etc so that's
one piece on the other end the world
desperately needs emergent leaders you
know this is a second side of the coin
we need people more than ever right now
to be fully deployed we need people to
find a way to grab an aspect of the
dragon's tail and pull you know and it's
it's overwhelming so what do we do in
response to that
reductionistic approach that I found
helpful what does it mean to be fully
deployed I think it's a combination of
cultivating personal sovereignty and
giving your best gifts for the current
moment so we're gonna explore that a
little bit personal sovereignty is a
term that you may have heard before I
like this simple definition it's the
capacity to be responsive and not
reactive an example of a lack of
sovereignty that might all relate to is
if you have an argument with a loved one
and they say something that is otherwise
benign but for whatever reason you get
really your nervous system gets
activated and you find yourself yelling
at them or something like that you're
reacting there you can imagine that in a
moment like this in a moment like a
crisis this need is greater than ever so
how do we maintain our responsiveness
just to kind of contextualize this sorry
I'm just gonna move some zoom stuff
around a bit personal sovereignty is the
foundation for sense making and sense
making is a foundation for choice making
and choice making is our ability to
respond to the medic crisis it
ultimately comes down to the quality of
our decisions and so if we were not in a
position of sovereignty then our
decisions are gonna suffer in our
response to the medic crisis is going to
suffer and we all know the stakes are
incredibly high
so how can we begin to cultivate or
maintain our personal sovereignty the
first step is something incredibly
mundane and I don't think this will be a
surprise to many people but you need to
begin by managing our physiology and the
fundamentals for this have always been
the same they've never changed we need
to have good habits around sleep
nutrition exercise and meditation and
meditation is probably the most
controversial of the four items there
but any kind of mental practice that
allows you to inquire into the nature of
your own mind anything that allows you
to develop meta-level awareness on
what's happening and kind of loosen up
your ego so you're not having egoic
responses to things
like all these life practices and you
can imagine all the habits that kind of
go along with this
the next step is to manage your
addiction so going back to those tools
of escapism and I think this is really
beautifully summed up by something to
Val rather concept all modern diseases
are diseases of abundance we're
surrounded by supernormal stimuli you
know there's more drama in a single
Netflix movie than any of us will
experience probably throughout our
entire lives I mean that seems to be
changing in light of what's happening
right now but you get the idea or the
fact that right now
it's the ethical choice to get your food
delivered instead of going to the
grocery store and there's all these
processed food options that a lot of
people are going to partake in so if you
fall into these traps then you're
basically compromising your vehicle for
sense making a choice making you're
compromising your your sovereignty and I
just put a list of examples here and you
know you can pick your poison I'm sure
everyone will have your highlight a
couple things here so digital ego hits
so this is where you're you you make
decisions based on notifications that
pop up on your phone related to
relationships that you actually care
about but they aren't the highest
fidelity form of relating to those
people news is a big one that's been
affecting me and just feeds in general
where you click one thing and then next
thing you know you're you know you're on
Facebook for an hour
the
practice to respond to these addictions
I'm calling negations so how do you
negate your addictions such that you up
regulate your personal sovereignty and
the final one which admittedly is a it's
a much more complex discussion and kind
of beyond the scope of this initial
presentation is giving your best gifts
and the thing I'd like to highlight here
is if we improve our life practices and
if we negate if we become ascetics and
we negate Netflix and YouTube and all
these things and we up regulate our
personal sovereignty but just do it for
its own sake it's like building a
high-performance vehicle without any
intention to drive it we basically need
a direction to energize and justify this
project we need we need a why and I
think what's interesting about right now
is that all those big like open-ended
capital P questions about purpose are
being forced into something a lot more
urgent so I
a lot of people who have been trying to
figure out their wife for years and
they've done you know a bunch of
different practices to try to discern
that and it seems to be a never-ending
quest we can't really afford that right
now we need to find something a
provisional purpose something that our
environment immediately demands of us
and find a way that we can bring our
puzzle piece to to fit to that and so
that that's another element that's I
would say what personal sovereignty is
in service of and that's her best
attempt to response the meta-crisis so
if I were to tie all this together in a
problem statement I'd say how might we
cultivate or maintain personal
sovereignty and manage our addictions in
the face of the current pandemic beyond
this how can we equip ourselves to best
respond to the immediate needs around us
how do we bring ourselves to a
sustainable state where we are primed
and ready to give our best gifts for the
current moment that is the problem that
we're trying to solve
and my hypothesis is that the best way
to do this especially in a time of
socialized social isolation is through
digital mastermind groups these are
digital gangs that basically people you
can connect with online that that
carrier if you show up or not so it's
not just you alone in your room trying
to meditate every morning trying to go
to bed on time there's there are people
that actually care about your
performance here there are people that
care that you are giving your best gifts
for people that are challenging you
toward sovereignty
in order to give you a sense of the
power of this I want to kind of give you
a little visualization exercise these
are two famous Navy SEALs and I just
want you to imagine you can close your
eyes if you want imagine one of the
habits that you've had the greatest
difficulty breaking or making so
whatever's more salient to you like
let's say you eat too many carbohydrates
and you've always tried to quit sugar or
let's say you've always tried to go to
the gym daily but you know it's been
years that you've known what to do and
you still haven't done it just identify
one of those and just pay attention to
any sense of frustration that you have
with how long it's been that you've
known what to do but you've had
difficulty implementing the actions
now I want you to imagine all of a
sudden that your roommates are Navy
SEALs
and you still have the same habit the
same challenge but you're now living
with Jaco well link and David Goggins
and they wake up at 5:00 every morning
and they work out immediately after
waking out they take cold showers they
meditate daily they are completely on
top of their and they're always
performing
how do you feel about that habit does it
feel a little bit easier
now my sense is that if you're like most
people even that visualization kind of
gives you a clue that there's something
about relationships that's key to
personal sovereignty and that's that's
what we're gesturing towards with this
mastermind group perhaps perhaps we've
made a mistake in thinking that we can
do this alone perhaps we need to be
surrounded by people with standards of
excellence people that that can push us
so to close this up I just want to I
want to present a prototype for what
this could look like and this is based
on personal experiences that I've had
running mastermind groups in person with
people who live with in the same city as
me and with people who live in different
time zones people who live you know at
other ends of the globe and basically
these these will be three weeks Sprint's
where you have a dedicated period of
time where you're focused on cultivating
personal sovereignty or giving your best
gifts there are three weeks because
they're long enough to be challenging
and impactful but not too long to lose
motivation another hypothesis is that
three members per group is best so in my
mind this is the maximum out of
accountability with a minimal amount of
risk each additional member starts to
increase the odds that somebody might
drop the ball and that starts to take
the wind out of everybody's sails and
then you start with three commitments so
going back to what we were talking about
before there's a life practice there's a
negation and there's a gift so just to
give you an example life practice could
be you're meditating every day negation
could be you're quitting YouTube for the
three week sprint and a gift could be
you are gonna be publishing an article
every week representing your perspective
on the meta-crisis something like that
and I think I have a final slide here
about what this could look like in terms
of the tools so yes one way that I've
done this is weekly housekeeping zoom
calls so once a week and
everybody sets a timer and you have ten
minutes to share what went on that week
and how you did with your life practices
negations and your gibbets while another
person jot down notes in a collective
Google Doc and then there's five minutes
for the group to respond so you can
source the collective intelligence and
then you switch until you're done
there's also a whatsapp group where
everybody can quickly talk to each other
or share their struggles throughout the
week and then there's some form of
commitment tracking so I've had
experience with using Google sheets or
air table to keep tabs on all those
habits that you're trying to cultivate
this is an MVP this might work for some
people and it might be terrible for
others it might be too structured it
might be not structured enough but my
idea here is to kind of throw this out
at the group and we can now switch to
kind of a group discussion and I can get
some reactions and maybe people can
share some of their personal experiences
and at the end we can talk about what it
might be like to actually sign up to do
something like this in the next three
weeks
so with that I'll switch it over to
Peter